"How to Treat Body Odor with Diet"
Vision is not the only
sense associated with
physical attractiveness
and partner preference.
Body odor signals a variety
of information on matters
such as eating habits,
hygiene, health, and more.
Based on a survey of hundreds
of college students,
men rated visual and smell
information as being equally important
for selecting a lover, while women
considered how their potential mates
smell to be the single
most important variable.
In other words, women ranked
body odor as more important
for attraction than ‘‘looks.’’
I’ve talked about the concern
around aluminum-
containing antiperspirants.
What can we do to make
ourselves smell better?
Clinical studies dating
back to the 1950s show
that chlorophyll can be used
to improve body odors.
This led to a wave of commercial
chlorophyll deodorant products.
But, as one chlorophyll
scientist lamented,
“because of the unfounded,
fantastic, and sometimes
completely idiotic claims
made for chlorophyll
by the promotion
and advertising men,
the buying public as well as
the scientist will remain skeptical,”
and rightly so.
To be an effective deodorant,
chlorophyll has to be taken
internally at doses
that far exceed those found
in so-called “deodorizing”
chewing gums and lozenges.
Studies showing the elimination
of detectable underarm odors
used doses on the order
of 100mg a day.
In other words, the amount
of chlorophyll one could get
in about a third of a bunch
of raw spinach.
So, before slathering
aluminum onto your skin,
I recommend first trying
to deodorize from the inside out
by eating a big salad every day,
which may improve your body odor
two ways, hitting
the chlorophyll threshold
and improving your health.
There is a scent to disease.
Some diseases result
in a characteristic odor
emanating from sick individuals.
For example,
tuberculosis of the throat
makes you smell like stale beer.
Typhoid makes you smell
like baked bread—
that doesn’t sound so bad—
though yellow fever makes
you smell like a butcher’s shop.
But it’s not just infection.
I mean evolutionarily,
wouldn’t it be advantageous
if you could smell
the first signs
of inflammation—immune
system activation—
to stay away from people before
they become contagious?
What this team
of researchers did
was inject people
with endotoxin,
which is a highly
inflammatory component
of certain bacterial
cell walls.
Caused a big spike
of internal inflammation,
and the question is:
Could you smell it on people?
Within just a few hours,
endotoxin-exposed individuals
had a more aversive body odor
relative to when they
were exposed to a placebo:
a significantly less pleasant
body odor within hours.
Moreover, the more inflamed
they got, the worse they smelled,
providing the first
experimental evidence
that we can smell
inflammation on people.
And guess where endotoxins
are found in the food supply?
Where bacteria
are found: in meat.
And they’re not
destroyed by cooking.
I have a whole series
of videos about that.
We know meat
causes inflammation.
So, does that mean
it makes people smelly?
You don’t know...until
you put it to the test.
“The effect of meat consumption
on body odor attractiveness.”
Not just body odor,
but body odor attractiveness.
For two weeks, male “odor
donors” were placed on a diet
that included meat or excluded
meat, a no-meat diet.
And then, during the final
24 hours, they had pads taped
into their armpits
to collect their body odor.
Then, the researchers
just needed some judges
to sniff the pads
from each of the men.
So, fresh odor samples—hot off
the pits, less than an hour old—
were assessed for their
pleasantness, attractiveness,
masculinity, and intensity
by 30 women.
A month later, the study
was repeated with the same guys,
but now following
the other diet.
The same poor women
were used as judges.
The men, incidentally,
were paid 2,000 in Czech currency
for their time
and “potential inconvenience
caused by the prescribed diet.”
But the women who had to sniff
all those armpit pads?
The raters were not paid
for their participation,
though did get a chocolate bar
after the second session.
So, who had the most pleasant,
the most attractive body odor?
The results showed
that “the odor of donors
when on the non-meat diet
was judged
as significantly more attractive,
more pleasant, and less intense.”
No difference was
noted for masculinity.
The researchers concluded that meat
may have a “negative impact
on perceived body
odor hedonicity.”
In other words,
those eating more plant-based
evidently smell significantly
more pleasurable.